in this video we'll look at how the Lac
operon functions in
eoli this is the Lac operon here you can
see the three structural genes Lac Z Lac
Y and Lac a Lac Z encodes the protein
beta
galactosidase Lac y encodes the enzyme
permease and Lac a encodes the protein
transacetylase all three of these
proteins work together to help the cell
bring in and break down lactose when
it's available in the environment
lactose is a sugar that the cell can use
for energy and
growth so these genes all share a
promoter and an operator further
Upstream of the Lac operon you see the
regulatory Gene Lac ey which encodes an
active
repressor the cell wants to be able to
break lactose down when it's present so
expression of these genes is necessary
when lactose is present in the
environment when lactose is not present
it would be a waste of the cell's energy
and resources to continue to make these
proteins so transcription of these
structural genes will be
limited so how does the cell alter
structural gene expression when lactose
is absent from the environment the Lac
eye repressor is active it binds to the
operator and prevents RNA polymerase
from binding to the promoter this limits
transcription of the lack genes in this
state the operon is said to be
repressed when lactose is present in the
cell the low concentration of
metabolizing proteins that are always
available start to convert lactose into
Alo lactose this Alo lactose acts as an
inducer binding to the Lac ey repressor
making it
inactive the repressor becomes inactive
because The Binding of alol lactose
causes its DNA binding domain to change
shape so it's unable to attach to the
DNA operator
in this state the repressor cannot block
The Binding of RNA polymerase to the
promoter and therefore transcription of
the structural genes can occur this
means that the lack proteins are
produced and the cell is able to break
down lactose at a higher rate in this
state the operon is said to be induced
by the presence of
lactose the Lac operon is said to be
inducible because lactose must be
present for the structural genes of the
operon to be
expressed that's the Lac operon when
lactose is present the repressor is
inactive and the genes that encode the
proteins that help break down lactose
are
expressed when lactose is absent the
repressor is active and the cell limits
production of those lactose metabolizing
proteins as a way to save energy and
resources if you'd like to delve deeper
into the Lac operon check out out my
Advanced La operon video if you want to
learn about another operon check out my
video on the trip operon